put it in my ears
[Music]
okay so today we will be showing how to
construct a 1920s style tube amplifier
including
making the tubes for it
this was a really fun project and I
think it turned out really good
so please enjoy
okay so we are going to start the
construction by making the base stems
for the two tubes here's an example
right here
you can see it has copper leads coming
out of the bottom to connect to the tube
and those are spot welded with a tiny
piece of nickel to a piece of tungsten
wire that forms the actual hermetic seal
and then up here there is a piece of
Steel that welds to the tungsten that we
connect to inside the tube
so let's just get started on making that
okay so we have our copper wires here
and we have our strip of nickel and what
we do is we just put this on the end
like that
then we take our cutters
okay so it's now time to weld on our
tungsten wire that's going to make the
actual seal in the glass I'm using 0.24
millimeter tungsten wire
and I just polished that to a mirror
finish using 220 grit sandpaper
and we are just going to weld like a
centimeter or so
to each one of these and cut it off
all right
okay so we're now going to make the top
part that's going to go inside the tube
I have this piece of Steel that I heated
up in the flame to
outgass it I'm just gonna
okay so we got these made now we're
going to weld them on
but first we're going to
just very gently
crimp the ends
just a little bit to put a little flat
spot on there
to make it easier to weld
okay so that's what the electrodes are
going to look like
now we can get started on actual glass
work we're going to have to make the
flare that these pinch into
[Music]
foreign
[Applause]
[Music]
foreign
so we have our two flares
and now we have to expand the glass out
such that we can fit our wires
foreign
now before we conceal
these wires in the pinches we just made
we have to make a oxide coating on the
surface of the tungsten
in order to create a hermetic seal in
the glass
and to do that we're just going to heat
these in the torch on low heat
and then we're going to clean it off
with a little bit of flux remover and
then we're going to heat it up one more
time just to drive off any remaining
solvent and I've had pretty good luck
with that giving me the correct seal
color
foreign
[Applause]
[Laughter]
okay that's what it's going to look like
now we just have to seal it in the glass
[Applause]
foreign
[Music]
[Applause]
okay I'll wait for that to cool and I'll
take a look at the seal color
foreign
okay so I ended up making a few
different seals here's one of them
I just have it in this tube filled with
acetone because it gives us a bit of
magnification so it can get a better
look
and you can see right at the bottom
right here we have the correct seal
color
and that would work you only need a
millimeter or two of that correct golden
color of the tungsten to make a good
seal but it's really not ideal we would
really like to use that entire length of
wire
so I gave it another shot
got this seal
see that one's better use about half the
tungsten this one we use pretty much all
of it that one these are about halfway
up there
like
if you're able to
get the whole length
that's really really what you want to
aim for uh
having the seal that looks like this
with the correct color going all the way
you can be a hundred percent sure that
that's not going to leak whatsoever that
having the text in this correct color is
pretty much the best way to make sure
that you have a good seal through the
glass
okay so we're going to start
constructing the tube elements now
cut these off
so this one on the end is going to be
the plate and I'm going to cut that
short
this one is going to be one of the
filament supports this one's going to be
a grid
this is going to be the other filament
support
we're going to do for the one in the
middle is we're going to
cut it off short
just bend it over
and that's what the
wire Arrangement is going to look like
so now we're going to make the grids for
these two tubes
and that's going to be pretty much the
only difference between these two tubes
this one's going to be a voltage
amplifier and for that we're going to
space the grid closer together that will
give us a higher voltage gain but less
current will be able to flow through the
tube because the grid itself it
restricts the flow of electrons
so if you have it closer together less
electrons will be able to get through
this one's going to be the power
amplifier and we just want a whole bunch
of current to be able to flow through
this
so we're going to space the grid wider
apart for that
and for that I'm just going to take this
copper wire
and I'm just going to wind it around
this form right here and maybe do about
like
10 or 11 turns or so
okay here are the finished grids
I went ahead and I crimped some nickel
on the end there
and these are just going to weld on
right there
foreign
for the plates we're going to use this
nickel sheet
and what we're going to do to connect it
the bottom here
we're going to cut off
a strip on each side right here and just
leave a little tab in the middle
that we're going to bend around
that connection right there
so it will all be one piece
foreign
and before I weld it
down there I'm going to weld an extra
piece of nickel at the top right here to
attach the getter
this is going to be the support for the
upper connection to the filament
to keep the filament under tension we
need to put a spring at the top
and we're going to use the 0.24
millimeter tuxton wire for that again
and we're just going to bend this
into sort of a
hook shape
and weld a bit of that on the top to act
as the spring
foreign
now we've got to attach the filament
and for that I'm using 0.11 millimeter
tungsten wire
and I just have a little piece of nickel
spot welded on the end
and we just got to fish this through
and weld it on the bottom
okay so now we're going to make the
getter
I'm going to use 20 gauge titanium wire
and I'm just going to wind
three Loops of it on here and weld each
one
okay this one is done now we're going to
make an envelope for it
got to make the evacuation stem now
[Music]
foreign
we're going to attach the evacuation
stem
[Music]
okay so we got to cut this to length now
this has got to go in there like that
we have about half inch of extra glass
at the bottom we have to get rid of
so what we're going to do is we're going
to score this around
and then we're going to heat up a piece
of glass very hot and just press it
right there where the crack is and
hopefully the crack will
propagate around and it will make us a
relatively clean break
thank you
okay let's try to whack it
okay
not quite even but we can just nip that
off with some pliers and that will be
fine while we're at it
I'm gonna take this off
[Music]
[Applause]
okay let's try to give this a test fit
okay so it looks like we're hitting
right there
so I'm going to take this to the grinder
and I'm just going to knock a little bit
of glass off there
okay so this
fits in there nicely
so now we're just going to wash it off
in some acetone
and then heat it a little bit with the
Torches to drive off the acetone vapor
and then we should be ready to seal that
in this
foreign
let's give it a shot
[Applause]
Okay so we've got the tube on the pump
and I'm gonna check it for leaks using
the high voltage Supply
[Music]
we have no blue glow at all and that
tells us we have a good seal
[Music]
so now what we're going to do is we're
just going to heat this up with the
torch to try to outgass it and once
we've done that for a while we're going
to hook the bombarder up to this to
drive the plate to red heat to try to
outgass that as well
[Music]
okay so I have the tube hooked up to the
tube tester and I'm gonna see if I'm
able to
get some life out of it
[Music]
yeah looks like we're getting some
France conductance out of it
[Music]
okay so we got the tube hooked up to the
Bombardier
uh that's this right here this can
supply 500 volts up to 200 milliamps but
um we'll probably only get about 25
through this tube but that's still like
about 12 Watts or so
so we'll we'll still get this plate uh
red hot and that will hopefully drive
out any gas frappy in it
[Music]
so I'm going to bring that up to
500 volts
and I'm going to bring up the filament
voltage
[Music]
right now we're only getting about 10
milliamps through there
[Music]
thank you
okay so we can see the plate is starting
to glow red
we're passing about 25 milliamps through
the tube
just paying about 12 Watts or so
and I'm just going to let it sit like
this for a few minutes to try to get out
as much gas as I can and then slowly
ramp it back down
[Music]
foreign
up to the tube tester again
[Music]
looks like it's still working
so I'm just going to heat together a
small amount with the induction heater
just to drive out any last bits of gas
that are trapped into it we'll seal it
off and then we'll heat together once
again once it's sealed
[Music]
foreign
Let's test it
okay so I have the tube hooked up and
let's see if it still works
okay that looks like it's working
so that's adjusting the plate voltage
the grid voltage
and this is adjusting the drive
so that seems to be working
okay let's finish the next one
[Applause]
okay so this is the starting point of
the tube amp so I'm going to build it on
this piece of wood
uh
I have this old uh
tin plated copper wire that I'm going to
use for the connections and uh
just going to use these brass nails for
the posts into the wood
and all the components we need we're
just going to attach them to nails that
are hammered in here so I think I'm just
going to start by uh
putting the strips down for the ground
and the high voltage
by pulling the wire like this we can get
it completely straight without any kinks
in it
okay so those are bent
foreign
and I'm just going to use that to get
the pattern for the nails and we're
going to put these tubes on
last
because there's other stuff we gotta
nail on here and I don't want to subject
these to that vibration too much
okay so here's how it's mocked up right
now
I looked through my collection of dog
bone resistors
and I was able to pick out a few that I
think will work for this
for the first stage I'm going to use a
1.5 Meg for the input resistor to the
first grid to ground
and then I think I'm going to try to do
a 130k plate resistor for the first tube
and then there's also going to be a
choke
in the plate Circuit of this tube
because I find that that increases
volume a little bit
then we're going to have a
435k resistor right here from the second
grid to ground
and then we're using
another one of those Transformers is the
output transformer for this
these have a primary resistance of about
700 ohms and then a secondary resistance
of a few ohms so I hope those will be an
Okay match for these tubes
but uh that will be seen
so I think I'll just start by getting
these uh
resistors soldered in there
okay here it is so far
I have these three resistors installed
we also have the schematic right here
here are those three resistors
and uh
change the wiring a little bit
previously I was going to wire these
tubes in parallel
but I think it's going to be a better
idea to wire them in series because it
will decrease the current required and
we'll also be able to get away with just
having one
variable resistor
for their filament adjustment
is able to find this old
filament riostat
it will work pretty good
and as far as these Transformers go I'm
going to use these doorbell Transformers
this one right here is just going to act
like a choke to give us a little bit
more
audio volume on the first stage and I'm
going to use the second one as the audio
output Transformer
and uh I can't bring myself to
cut off the prongs right here so we're
just going to mount them on a few pieces
of wood
something like that
and that should look halfway decent
but
tons
foreign
[Music]
okay here's how it looks so far
unfortunately the tube that was going to
be in this position uh
got a pretty hard whack and it ended up
uh breaking the filament so I had to put
in a different tube that I already had
so that's a bit unfortunate
but now we're at the point where we have
to get these leads soldered to these
nails and at first I was just going to
bend them around and solder them but uh
that's actually going to be a pretty
tough thing to try to do and undo if I
need to swap
tubes in and out
so I have these little uh
pieces of brass shim
and I'm gonna cut a slot into them have
a tiny hole in the middle
and basically just slip them
in the middle of each one of these nails
and that will give me sort of a platform
to solder to without having to bend the
leads and if I have to unsolder them I
can quickly just heat this up and pull
it back up again
foreign
so I think I'm going to end up just
pulling the nails out
sliding them underneath that might end
up being just as much trouble as cutting
a slot in these
okay so this is how those turned out I
think they look pretty good
so the last thing to do is uh
get this control mounted this is going
to be the filament riostat
and then after that we can get the tube
soldered in and start to test this thing
I thought you guys might want a quick
look inside this very very old riostat
so I took the cover off
and it's actually has uh gearing in it
so here's the resist resistance wire
right here
and then there's a little gear reduction
to give you a fine control over that
very very complicated
kind of over engineered but pretty
pretty cool looking
so as you can see this control is
missing a lead
so we got to attach something to that I
think I'm gonna
cut off another small piece of brass
for that
Okay so we've got a brass strip right
here and we've drilled five holes
through it such that when we solder this
uh the solder is going to have support
from both sides of the metal
there's our fixed control
trying to figure out how to mount it
either could take a piece of metal
bend it from here bend it down at an
angle mounted like that or I could do it
with a piece of wood
something like that
main issue is going to be trying to have
it
stiff because it's going to be sort of
cantilevered over here and you
try to turn the knob and it could be
really weak right here so
that's going to be non-trivial to figure
out
okay so for mounting the riostat I'm
going to cut out a piece of brass for
that this is just a
a brass cover that would go on a door
or something like that
and I think I'm just gonna
do something like this
I'm gonna do a rough rough shape like
this
and
once we cut it out we'll make it all
pretty
[Music]
foreign
got a hollow brass tube that is
sharpened at the end
I'm just gonna punch a hole
and I'm just going to bend the paper
foreign
s the pot
and we're going to use that to make our
Center hole
foreign
okay so for screws I got these
these are not ideal for wood
because they have a fine pitch thread so
probably to get enough grip we might
have to put a little Super Glue on these
when we screw these in
but that that should be fine no one will
know about that
so I'm just gonna
drill two pilot holes here and then
drill them out larger for the screws
foreign
last thing we've got to do
we got to get our coupling caps in there
I have a bunch of these old
I think they're Mica caps they might be
paper
I'm gonna have to test them to see if
they're leaky
looking through uh my old capacitors I
was initially going to go with these it
actually turns out that these are paper
on the inside so like they're they all
test a super leaky
um
I was able to find these uh these nice
Mica caps these are really really
overkill for this but they're one of the
few old caps I have
it's not going to be leaky
so I was able to get two of those
I'll just put one of them here
one of them here
something like that
and then we can finally call this done
okay we have got the tube amp hooked up
here's how it looks all finished up
hooked up to a speaker just a crappy
test speaker
the tube tester which will give us our
power
and for the signal Source I'm just using
an AM radio right there
okay let's see what it will do
put it in my ears
[Music]
of fire roaring at my back
as she disappeared
but soon
[Music]
lips
the way
is my story it's sad the truth
so as you can see it's not exactly Hi-Fi
I think that's due to uh the the mains
Transformers I'm using right here
probably not optimized for audio in any
way uh
also if you're doing a single-ended uh
tube amplifier like this you want a
Transformer that has a gap in the core
otherwise you can get a saturation in
the core and it will add distortion
so there is a a number of things uh
against us here
but you know it sort of works and
that's good enough for me uh pretty much
completely scratch Bill tube amplifier
kind of unique so that's pretty cool
thank you very much for watching
[Music]
[Applause]
the people
[Music]